Finding Aid for George S. Morris Papers 1852-1889 and 1910-1915
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George S. Morris Papers 1852-1889 1910-1915 1852-1889
Morris, George Sylvester, 1840-1889.
Professor of philosophy at Johns Hopkins University and University of Michigan. Correspondence; notes and lectures on philosophical topics, notably ethics, political philosophy, logic and aesthetics; diary and journal, including account of European trip, 1866-1867; photographs; and later materials collected by Robert M. Wenley preparatory to writing a biography of George S. Morris, 1910-1915.
852011 Aa 2 UAm
2 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred over from the Graduate Library (donor no. 1278 ) in 1953 which had received it from the Morris family.
The collection is open for research.
George Sylvester Morris, educator and philosopher, was born November 15, 1840 in Norwich, Vermont. He graduated from Dartmouth in 1861, then from 1862 to 1863, Morris served in the Union Army. In the fall of 1863, he joined the staff of Dartmouth as a tutor in Greek and Mathematics, a post he held for one year. In 1864, Morris entered the Union Theological Seminary, then in the period 1866-1868, he traveled to Europe to study at the University of Halle and the University of Berlin. In 1870 Morris became professor of modern languages at the University of Michigan; later, in 1885, he headed the university's philosophy department. Morris wrote on both Kant and Hegel and was a champion of the idealistic movement initiated by Kant. Morris died in Ann Arbor on March 23, 1889.
The collection consists of biographical information; correspondence; lectures, notes, and writings; miscellaneous materials from his student days at Dartmouth, Royalton Academy and Kimball Union Academy; diary and travel journals; and photographs.
Subjects:
Europe--Description and travel.; Johns Hopkins University.; Morris, George Sylvester, 1840-1889.; Philosophy.; Voyages and travels.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan. Department of Romance Languages.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Morris, George Sylvester, 1840-1889.; Living rooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Chamberlain, Joshua Lawrence, 1828-1914.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1831-1908.; Muirhead, John Henry, 1855-1940.; Schaff, Philip, 1819-1893.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Ueberweg, Friedrich, 1826-1871.; Ulrici, Hermann, 1806-1884.; Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical
  - Biographical memorials 1889 (Box 1)
    also includes letters of condolence
  - Report of faculty activities 1875/76 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes letters from Charles K. Adams, James B. Angell, Joshua L. Chamberlain, John Dewey, Henry S. Frieze, Daniel C. Gilman, John H. Muirhead, Philip Schaff, Moses C. Tyler, Friedrich Ueberweg, and Hermann Ulrici.
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1852-1865 (Box 1)
  - 1866-1889 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Friedrich Ueberweg 1869-1871 (Box 1)
  - Letters written to family members while traveling in Europe 1866-1868 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and other materials of Robert M. Wenley concerning proposed biography of Morris 1910-1915 (Box 1)
- Lectures, notes, writings
  - Speeches read before Shakespeare Club, Royalton Academy, Concord, N.H. 1861-1862, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Report of lecture on musical aesthetics 1887 (Box 1)
  - Lectures on political philosophy 1887, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes on political philosophy (Box 1)
  - Lectures on ethics Miscellaneous notes on ethics (Box 1)
  - Lectures on aesthetics circa 1887, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes on aesthetics (Box 1)
  - Lectures on logic (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes on logic (Box 1)
  - Notes on "National calamities incentives to national virtues? (Box 1)
  - Notes on Plato (Box 1)
  - Notes on Bacon (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings and other manuscripts, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts, including "Introduction" to Hegel's Philosophy of the State; writings on logic (Box 1)
- Dartmouth College
  - Master's oration 1864 (Box 1)
  - Compositions, essays, orations and speeches 1857-1865, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Master's thesis, "Spiritualization: the law and goal of human progress" 1864 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Royalton Academy and Kimball Union Academy (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Papers re. books and personal library (Box 1)
  - Invoices of book purchases and related materials (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Papers re. Roger Morris (Box 1)
  - Paper of Arlisle M. Young entitled, "Analysis of Introduction to Hegel's Aesthetics" 1889 (Box 1)
- Bound records
  - Journals 1856-1861 (Box 2)
  - Journal of European Trip 1866-1867, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Diary, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Lectures on Psychology by Prof. Friedrich A. Trendelenburg (Box 2)
    (summarized by G.S. Morris)
  - Scrapbook containing reviews of Kant's Critique and Morris' Hegel's Philosophy of the state and of history, 1881-1888 (Box 2)
  - University class lectures on logic (Box 2)
  - Notebook on logic (Box 2)
  - Notebook on Goethe (Box 2)
  - Philosophy index (Box 2)
- Photographs (Box 2)
  - Portraits; also interiors and exteriors of Morris' home (Folder UAm)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.
Nov. 12, 1885; Aug. 15, 1885
Chamberlain, Joshua Lawrence, 1828-1914.
Oct. 9, 1872
Dewey, John, 1859-1952.
May 9, 1910; Dec. 6, 1915 [letters located in folder of materials collected by Robert M. Wenley]
Frieze, Henry Simmons, 1817-1889.
Sept. 8, 1870; Nov. 21, 1884
Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1831-1908
Feb. 4, 1879
Muirhead, John Henry, 1855-1940
Oct. 31, 1887; Dec. 12, 1887
Schaff, Philip, 1819-1893
Feb. 25, 1871; Mar. 9, 1871
Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900
Nov. 15, 1885; June 27, 1885; Nov. 13, 1885
Ueberweg, Friedrich, 1826-1871.
1869-1871 [in specially designated folder]
Ulrici, Hermann, 1806-1884.
Nov. 21, 1867; 1874?